Okay בוקר טוב.
boker tov. Since we begin the second דף daf of יבמות, Yevamot,
which of course is why we're דף ג׳ daf gimmel
today. Thank you to Michael for getting us started. I know Michael
gave a whole introduction, I'll just say then a few brief words,
maybe some of it I'm sure a good amount will be repetitive
but just to say my own very brief introduction. First of all,
we're beginning סדר נשים. Seder Nashim. סדר נשים Seder Nashim is generally
translated of course as women. But a very reasonable suggestion has been
made that it might be the proper translation is actually wives. Because
אשה, Isha, so you say שלמה Shlomo had many נשים, Nashim, it
doesn't mean women, it means wives. So actually the same plural would
apply and so much of the tractates are about issues relating to
wives. יבמות, Yevamot, גיטין, Gittin, קידושין, Kiddushin, even נדרים, Nedarim, so much
of that in the תורה Torah although it's also about young daughters,
daughters under age, but it's about the husband or the father annulling.
So that's interesting to think about in general in terms of how
women what their general sort of assumed role and being treated as
a subject matter would be. It's also a very challenging and difficult
מסכת masechet to begin the סדר seder with, it's not great for
the דף יומי, Daf Yomi, the סדרא sidra ordered by the largest
מסכתות masechtas first. So you first have שבת Shabbat and עירובין, Eruvin,
these huge מסכתות, masechtos, judged by number of פרקים. prakim. For דף
יומי Daf Yomi purposes, it would have been good if it had
been reversed order. Get people in low and then build them up
to it. So we are starting with a very big מסכת masechet
which is going to last us for many months. I think we'll
end around President's Day.
While of course a good part of it deals with the actual
מצוה mitzvah of יבום, yibum, it should be mentioned that an equal
important section of it deals with general issues related about personal status.
And therefore questions about ממזר, mamzer, about who can marry in and
not, פצוע דכא, ptzu daka, כרות שפכה, krus shepcha, questions about people
that you're not sure what their Jewish status is. Or you're not
sure about whether who their parents well who their father is and
so on. Issues about people that כהנים, Kohanim, women that כהנים Kohanim
cannot marry. So basically an enormous amount even גירות, gerus, an enormous
is in here. So basically pretty much everything you'd expect relating to
issues of personal status are found in יבמות, Yevamot, also issues about
עגונה agunah even though you would expect to find that in גיטין,
Gittin, but a question of a husband's woman has died or not
and trusting a single witness to testify about that. It's worth sort
of approaching it that way rather than approaching it like we're going
to have digressions. We're in יבמות Yevamos with a lot of digressions.
Really this is the מסכת masechet that deals with issues around personal
status after you get after the מצוה mitzvah of יבום. yibum. Also
we should just say the literal meaning of the word יבם yabam
or יבמה yevama is brother-in-law and sister-in-law.
Although the מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum is translated as levirate marriage,
I don't even know why but where the word levirate comes from,
it has anything to do with
לוי, Levi, לוי. Levi. But anyway, it doesn't only mean the person
to whom you do יבום yibum for as the person who does
יבום. yibum. It's not only sort of the technical term relating to
the מצוה. mitzvah. A יבמה yevama is a sister-in-law and a יבם
yabam is a brother-in-law but obviously it also has a technical sense
as well. And as I know that Michael discussed with you, we
definitely find יבום yibum before מתן תורה Matan Torah by יהודה Yehuda
and תמר. Tamar. We also find it by רות Ruth where it's
not clear that that's יבום, yibum, it sounds like a lot of
things around there sound like יבום, yibum, but we're not dealing with
brothers.
And that leads רמב"ן Ramban to say that יבום yibum existed in
ancient cultures pre-מתן תורה Matan Torah and it even existed not with
the brother, but existed with any relative, or any I guess male
relative obviously.
And seeing echoes in that in the רות Ruth story. And then
saying but the תורה Torah came and because of the prohibition of
עריות arayot forbade it in general but did allow it to remain
in the one case by the issue of brothers. And it does
raise the whole interesting point about what does it mean why is
it so important what does it mean להקים שם
אחיו המת. lehakim shem achiv hamet. It certainly does not mean that
the child born from the union should be given just literally the
name
after the father, we don't find that at all in the תורה,
Torah, we don't find it in the story of יהודה Yehuda and
תמר. Tamar.
In fact it was יהודה׳ס Yehuda's desire
to name the child, right? The good point too why does it
require the act of יבום? yibum? And it does seem more that
there is something metaphysical going on, the רמב"ן Ramban hints to the
idea of גלגול נשמות gilgul neshamot of some type of a reincarnation
of the dead brother's soul that somehow maybe may be possible when
the conception comes from... to a family member somehow that allows for
some type of this reincarnation, even if you don't believe in the
reincarnation, but there clearly seems to be something deeper on a metaphysical
level that when this happens through a family member somehow the child
is more a real continuity of the dead father. And for הלכה
halakha purposes, what it means has a lot to do with issues
of inheritance and who inherits the dead father's property, but we will
see that that's not necessarily a unanimous or a consensus. And the
last thing that I'll say about that what's fascinating is because of
the challenge in so much of what we'll be dealing with is
the idea of does the מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum override the
biblical prohibition of a dead brother's sister? So if the brother died
and there were children or other reasons why the woman is פטור
patur in יבום yibum like the whole issues of צרות tzarot that
we're seeing in the opening משנה, mishna, I mean of ערווה erva
וצרת ערווה, ve-tzarat erva, that then there's an איסור כרת issur kares
for one brother to marry his, I said brother's sister, I meant
brother's wife, for him to marry his dead brother's wife. And that's
an איסור כרת. issur kares. But to deal with that,
the non-rabbinic Jews, קראים Karaites and the what do you call it
the I think it was the צדוקים Tzadukim or the אסיים. Eseiyim.
I think it's the אסיים. Eseiyim. Anyway, had different interpretations. So the
קראים Karaites said that fascinating idea. They said that the תורה Torah
actually only allows יבום yibum in a case when it's not the
brother. That when it says אחים, achim, it means אחים achim loosely,
like אברהם Avraham says to לוט, Lot, הלא אנשים אחים אנחנו, halo
anashim achim anachnu, and it doesn't mean brother, and the only time
the מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum would apply would be in a
case like רות Rut where you're related but you're not a forbidden
ערווה erva relationship. And that's how they sort of deal with that
problem of it running up against the איסור ערווה. issur erva. I
think it's the אסיים Eseiyim or somebody else wanted to claim that
יבום yibum was only by אירוסין eirusin not נישואין, nissu'in, other ways
of dealing with the problem that it's going against an איסור ערווה
issur erva of brother's wife. Of course for חז"ל Chazal that is
the whole חידוש chiddush of יבום yibum and that's actually what we're
going to get to today whether it fits in a normal pattern
of עשה דוחה לא תעשה asei doche lo ta'asei or is it
a more much more of a radical חידוש, chiddush, one of the
times where the תורה Torah says like two things were said בדיבור
אחד, be-dibbur echad, so sometimes it's like שמור וזכור shamor ve-zachor which
are not contradictory, they're two aspects of שבת Shabbat but it's dealing
with the difference of the עשרת הדיברות. aseret ha-dibrot. But more interestingly
is when it speaks about two things which are basically contradictory. And
the one of the best cases that the גמרא Gemara has of
that of נאמרו בדיבור אחד ne'emru be-dibbur echad in the sense that
yes they're contradictory and they're both
true is the איסור issur of אשת אח eshet ach and יבמה
יבוא עליה. yevama yavo aleha. So clearly that is one of the
fascinating aspects of יבום yibum is how it runs up against that
איסור ערווה. issur erva. And that's what I have to say for
the introduction. Charlie.
Levir is Latin for husband's brother.
Oh wow, fascinating. Okay. Yes.
How do you know that these relationships that the איסור issur outlives
the relationship? So for instance if your brother were to divorce his
wife.
Right, so that's a good question and we will be seeing that
because one of the things I should have said in addition to
status issues, one of the major things that יבמות Yevamot deals with
is איסור עריות issur arayot and הלכה halakhically defining the act of
sex which comes from פסוקים pesukim about יבום yibum and in general
issues around איסור עריות issur arayot and we are going to see
for example that wife's sister is learned to not continue after her
death because it says בחייה, be-chayeha, ואשה אל אחותה לא תקח לצרור
לגלות ערותה עליה בחייה. ve-isha el achota lo tikach litzror legalot ervata
aleha be-chayeha.
But in general these איסורים issurim are the default assumption should be
that it continues even after the relationship's severed unless you sort of
explicitly know otherwise like the case of the wife's sister. But we
will see that. But yes.
Thank you. That is interesting. You're saying if it's an idea of
let's say גלגול נשמות, gilgul neshamot, so let's say the guy who
died was a really bad guy, do you really want to bring
him back?
Oh, that's an interesting question whether does the about what he says
about the relationship about character and צדיק ורשע tzadik ve-rasha as opposed
to yeah okay that's a fascinating question. I don't know, basically I've
shared with you now about fifty percent of everything I know about
גלגול נשמות. gilgul neshamot. So anyway,
so now we will continue now on דף ג'. daf gimmel. Michael,
where did you leave us off?
Very very top.
Very first word, כולם. kulam.
Okay. So what we are finding now at the beginning of this
מסכת masechet is what we find at the beginning of many מסכתות
masechtot which is a opening סתם stam piece which is very technical
and very I mean not like conceptual I should say, very much
also about language and gets itself in a high very hyper-concerned
about a technical the grammar or language issue around the משנה. mishna.
So people know for example קידושין Kiddushin opens with why does it
say האישה נקנית ha-isha nikneit and not האיש קונה ha-ish koneh and
why does it use this language of קנין kinyan and not... That
language of קנין kinyan and it asks all these sort of questions
about the phrasing, or אור ארבעה, or arba'ah, what does אור or
mean, the phrasing of the משנה Mishnah generally understood that this is
a late one of the latest layers of the גמרא, Gemara, maybe
maybe even added after the general סתם Stam editing of the גמרא.
Gemara. This is based on a letter of רב שרירא גאון Rav
Sherira Gaon who points out that this often opens
מסכתות Masechtot and nothing new is actually said in these sections. It
was sometimes used as an opportunity to quote material that is coming
up later or to allude to
ideas or introduce ideas that will be relevant in the future discussions,
but it doesn't develop any new ideas itself. And that's what we're
going to pull up, that'll be half of today's דף Daf and
then the other half we'll actually turn to the core issue about
this idea of this idea of ערוה Ervah and צרת ערוה. Tzarat
Ervah. But right now we're dealing with the question about what was
the order of the משנה? Mishnah? Why did the משנה Mishnah start
when it talks about the
עריות Arayot that a you know that might be married to a
man's brother and therefore he can't do יבום Yibum with her or
with the co-wives, the צרות, Tzarot, who those עריות Arayot are? It
starts with his daughter and then you know granddaughter and then it
goes to his to his wife's daughter and his wife's you know
granddaughter, his father-in-law, his mother-in-law, his grandmother-in-law etc. So what is that
order about? So the first thing the גמרא Gemara says is is
that maybe it's because let's actually read from the bottom of דף
ב' עמוד ב'. Daf Bet Amud Bet. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
אלא בתו, Ella Bito, last line on דף ב' עמוד ב'. Daf
Bet Amud Bet. The reason it starts with daughter is כיון דאתי
מדרשא חביבא ליה. keivan de'ati midrasha chaviva lei. Because it's learned out
from a דרשא, drasha, it's not explicit in the verse, it's dear
to the תנא. Tanna. Sometimes an idea that the תנאים Tannaim are
more interested in quoting stuff that's part of their you know stuff
that they have sort of uncovered or revealed or interpreted rather than
things that are explicit in the verse. Now now what do you
mean that the daughter is not explicit? I mean the תורה Torah
חזי chazei says don't marry you
know a woman and her mother, a woman and her daughter and
so on. So the point is that every time the תורה Torah
speaks about marrying a woman and her daughter, it speaks about the
speaks about your wife's daughter. So for example, take a look רש"י
Rashi says, רש"י Rashi quotes the פסוק, pasuk, it says ערבת אשה
ובתה לא תגלה את בת בנה ואת בת בתה לא תקח לגלות
ערבתה,
ervat isha u'vitah lo tegaleh et bat bnah v'et
bat bitah lo tikach legalot ervatah, okay? So ערבת אשה
ובתה לא תגלה,
ervat isha u'vitah lo
tegaleh, okay and then it says את בת בתה ואת בת בנה
את בת בתה ואת בת בנה.
et bat bitah v'et bat bnah et bat bitah
v'et bat bnah. So so there you get daughter and granddaughters, okay
but again, my point about whether נשים nashim means women or wives,
you would have interpreted this I think most naturally as a woman
and her daughter, okay but the rabbis interpret it to be your
wife and her daughter. So man cannot cannot be married to or
have sex with his wife's daughter, but what about his biological daughter
that is not his wife's daughter, born to a woman that he
did not marry, okay is that where do we know that that
is forbidden on somebody? So the issue of בתו, bito, not בת
אשתו. bat isho. Like there could be בת אשתו bat isho who's
also בתו, bito, but somebody who's just בתו, bito, just his daughter
and not his wife's daughter, so it's his daughter from a non-marital
union, where do we know that's אסור? assur? That's never in the
תורה. Torah. And therefore we only learn it out from a דרשא
drasha and that's why it says מילתא דאיתא בדרשא milta de'ita bidrasha
something that was learned from a דרשא drasha חביבא ליה. chaviva lei.
Now we actually came across this in חגיגה Chagigah and I do
have to tell you that disturbingly the way the גמרא Gemara refers
to a biological daughter that is not a wife's daughter is בתו
מאנוסתו. bito me'anusato. And I really do not know why the גמרא
Gemara point gives the example of born from rape. Why didn't it
say בתו ממפותתו, bito mi'mefutato,
from the woman that he seduced if you wanted to use a
biblical you know you don't want to say extra-marital whatever there's not
a biblical category like that but there is a biblical category of
מפותה mefuta a woman that is seduced rather than a woman that's
raped.
And is פילגש... pilegesh...
Well yeah true. But but within the sort of עריות Arayot discussion
you know you have these categories. So it is disturbing that it
uses that example but that's biological daughter and that's not explicitly in
the פסוקים pesukim so therefore the גמרא Gemara says the תנא Tanna
would like to open with that. Okay so let's take a look.
So it says like this. כולו נמי מדרשא אתו. kulu nami midrasha
atu. The גמרא Gemara says I don't get it, all of the
cases in the משנה Mishnah the idea that there's an exemption of
יבום Yibum when you're dealing with an ערוה Ervah is not explicit
in the פסוקים pesukim it's learned out from a דרשא drasha which
we'll get to. So all the עריות Arayot all the fifteen women
that are עריות Arayot are their exempt status of יבום Yibum is
learned from a דרשא, drasha, why is בתו bito being privileged here,
being listed first? So the גמרא Gemara says no, נהי דענין יבום
אתיין מדרשא, nehi de'inyan Yibum atyan midrasha, it's true relating to יבום
Yibum aspect the exemption from יבום Yibum all these עריות. Arayot. עריות
arayot are learned out from a דרשה, drasha, but עיקר איסורייהו בהדיא
כתיב והוא. ikkar issuraihu bahedaya ketiv v'hu.
The basic fact that it is an עריות, arayot, that's explicit in
the פסוקים. psukim. בתו, bito, but a man's biological daughter who is
not his wife's daughter, עיקר איסורא מדרשה. ikkar issura midrasha. The fundamental
prohibition comes, we only learn out from a דרשה, drasha, from a,
you know, a Rabbinic interpretation, not an explicit verse. דאמר רבא d'amar
Rava because רבא Rava says, אמר ליה רב יצחק בר אבדימי, amar
leh Rav Yitzchak bar Avdimi, אתיא הנה הנה אתיא זימה זימה. atya
heina heina, atya zima zima. We make a גזירה שוה gezeira shava
from the words הנה הנה heina heina and זימה זימה. zima zima.
So what's the גזירה שוה? gezeira shava? So here it says by,
meaning the funny thing is that it says that a man cannot
have sex with his granddaughter, okay, and biological granddaughter even not his
wife's child, you know, not descendant from his wife. So the גמרא
Gemara says, well if you can't have sex with your granddaughter, קל
וחומר kal vachomer with your daughter, but you can't get punished or
warned from a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, you need an explicit verse.
Okay, so number one, even though you do have a verse for
granddaughter. So where is, but there is a גזירה שוה gezeira shava
to tell you that it's forbidden. What's the גזירה שוה? gezeira shava?
So רש״י, Rashi, so where's רש״י Rashi say? Says,
okay, רש״י Rashi doesn't quote the whole גזירה gezeira like. Let's see,
one minute.
Yes, one minute. A
minute.
Okay,
so it says by the case of biological granddaughter, it
says, it says, את בת בנו, et bat bno, no, it says
what, what's the פסוק? pasuk? ערבת בת בנך, ervat bat bincha,
thank you,
ערבת בת בנך או בת בתך. ervat bat bincha o bat bitecha.
So notice again, it's granddaughter, but it mentions no wife, so it's
biological, right? לא תגלה ערבתן כי ערבתך הנה. lo tegaleh ervatan ki
ervat-cha heina.
Thank you, לא תגלה ערבתן כי ערבתך הנה.
lo tegaleh
ervatan
ki ervat-cha heina.
Okay, כי ערבתך הנה. ki ervat-cha heina. Okay,
so that's that word of הנה. heina. Okay, and so that's the
הנה heina and there's another פסוק pasuk that says שארה הנה זימה
היא. sh'eira heina zima hi. Okay,
which is in versus what, what's that פסוק pasuk there? אשה ובתה.
isha u'vito. Okay, thank you, אשה ובתה
לא תגלה
שארה
הנה.
isha u'vito lo tegaleh sh'eira
heina.
It's בת בנה ובת
בתה.
bat
bno u'bat bito.
בת בנה, bat bno, right, I know, בת בתה, bat bito, right,
שארה הנה. sh'eira heina. ושארה הנה זימה היא. v'sh'eira heina zima hi.
Okay,
so what we say is like this. So here because you have
הנה heina here by biological granddaughter and you have הנה heina here
by wife's, you know, sort of granddaughter and granddaughter. So we say
that the same way here daughter is prohibited just like granddaughter, so
here granddaughter is prohibited, daughter is also prohibited. So we know that
daughter is prohibited based on the הנה הנה heina heina linking biological
granddaughter to wife's granddaughter. Okay, so that gets us, so the הנה
heina gets us the idea that the daughter is also prohibited. You
people get that now? The זימה זימה zima zima tells you that
it's punished by, that it's equally punished punished by שריפה, sreifa, by
burning, by you know, by execution of the court because it says
here, it says שארה הנה זימה היא. sh'eira heina zima hi. And
it says by another פסוק pasuk רש״י Rashi quotes, hold
on, באש ישרפו אתו ואתהן. ba-esh yisrefu oto v'et-hen. One minute, זימה
היא באש ישרפו אתו
ואתהן,
zima hi
ba-esh
yisrefu oto
v'et-hen, right, was it? I think I think I think that's by
אשה ובתה, isha u'vito, right? ולא תהיה זימה.
v'lo tihye
zima. Okay, so by again, by wife's daughter and granddaughter it says
באש ישרפו אתה ואתהן, ba-esh yisrefu ota v'et-hen, right, ולא תהיה זימה
v'lo tihye zima בתוככם betochechem
20:14.
So again, by wife you have the idea of not only granddaughter
but daughter, and by wife you have the idea of שריפה, sreifa,
punishable by death. So the so the הנה heina gets us to
learn from the wife example that biological includes daughter and sort of
through a daisy chaining because it doesn't say זימה zima up here,
but through a daisy chaining once it's linked to this word of
הנה, heina, that's linked there and then הנה heina is linked to
זימה zima and זימה zima gets you down here, right? So you
see how you get that? Right. So then if we're going to
learn the prohibition of daughter, we're also going to learn that it's
also from שריפה. sreifa. Okay? So you have a פסוק pasuk of
biological where it only mentions granddaughter and it doesn't mention the punishment.
By wife it mentions daughter and granddaughter and it mentions the punishment.
So the הנה heina gets us to the daughter and the הנה
heina through the זימה zima gets us to the שריפה. sreifa. Okay?
So that's acceptable to derive from.
Yes, it's only by קדשים kodashim you're not allowed to do that.
Okay, by other things... Okay anyway, so that's how we learn daughter
from a פסוק pasuk and that's why we wanted to start with
it. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: השתא דאמרת כל
מילתא דאתיא מדרשה חביבא ליה. Hashta de'amarta kol milta de'atya midrasha chaviva
lei. One minute, if the תנא Tanna prefers, you know, it's dear
to him things that are learned out from a דרשה, drasha,
so ליתני לאחות אשתו לבסוף. lisni la'achot ishto libasof. So then the
one thing that is, that you know, that is not learned out
from a דרשה drasha is the case of אחות אשתו, achot ishto,
because the, as we're going to find out, the wife's sister, the
idea that an ערווה erva is exempt from יבום yibum starts from
a פסוק pasuk by wife's sister. That's what we're going to see
when we turn the page. Okay, so it's saying like this, it's
saying you started with בתו.
bito. Let's talk about what the list of the משנה Mishnah is.
Okay, so the משנה Mishnah first has בתו bito and then all
of the things related
to
בתו bito like בת בתו bat bito etc., etc. Then it has
בת אשתו, bat ishto, right, and בת בתו bat bito etc., right?
So you have
בת בתו. bat bito. You have בתו bito number one, then בת
אשתו, bat ishto, then what's the next series?
חמותו? chamoto? Okay, so you have חמותו. chamoto. Okay, so notice these
are all one generation, these are down or up, right? אם חמותו
em chamoto etc. and then you know and then just continuing the
list. Okay, so you have daughter and essentially a mother or mother-in-law,
yes. And then what? אחותו מאמו. achoto me'imo. Okay, then you have
אחותו. achoto.
Okay, and אחות achot this, אחות achot that,
right, אחות achot this, אחות achot that. And then one generation up
as well, so the sister idea, yes.
And then you have three אשת, eshet, and then three things through
wife. אשת אחיו מאמו. eshet achiv me'imo. What was the other
אשת?
אחיו שלא
היה בעולמו.
eshet achiv
shelo haya beolamo
And then you have כלתו. kallato.
כלתו kallato and כלתו kallato is what?
The last one.
Yeah, but what is it? It's essentially אשת בנו, eshet bno, okay,
אשת בנו eshet bno which is called כלתו. kallato. Okay, so you
have three cases of wife. Okay, so do you see how it's
organized? Daughter, mother, sister, wife. Is that clear to people how that's
organized? Okay. So what it's saying is, so you want to start
with daughter because the whole prohibition of daughter is learned out from
a דרשה, drasha, but basically we're prioritizing things learned out from a
דרשה. drasha. Fine, but it says, so that's the, everything else is
explicit in the פסוק. pasuk. That's the only עריות arayot learned out
from a דרשה. drasha. But everything else, the fact that an ערווה
erva is exempt from יבום yibum is also a דרשה. drasha. The
one thing that's not a דרשה, drasha, I mean it is a
דרשה, drasha, but it's okay, not as much of a דרשה, drasha,
is wife's sister. That thing, that she is an ערווה erva and
exempt from יבום, yibum, the גמרא Gemara feels is more explicit in
the פסוק. pasuk. So if the general rule is prioritizing the דרשות,
drashot, the very last thing that should have been mentioned should have
been wife's sister, which is, where is it? אחות אשתו. achot ishto.
Where's אחות אשתו
achot
ishto in this?
In the אחות achot list?
The third thing, right?
Oh, אחות אשתו, achot ishto, one of them is אחות אשתו, achot
ishto, right?
In the אחות achot list? Yes. Okay, fine. Okay, so why if
we're prioritizing דרשות drashot and more explicit is at the end, אחות
אשתו, achot ishto, which is explicit not only that she's forbidden but
that she's exempt יבום, yibum, should be the last thing listed? Why
is she not the last thing listed if that really is the
organizing principle? So let's take a look. So it says like this:
ליתני לאחות אשתו לבסוף. lisni la'achot ishto libasof. But it says no.
איידי דאיירי באיסור אחוותא, aidei de'ayei be'issur achvaso, since we started talking
about, about, you know, sort of siblings, תנא אחות אשתו, tana achot
ishto, right? Then we tossed, you know, so it says basic point.
Yeah, after we got through the daughters and the mothers, the next
thing to go with is sisters and we mentioned wife's sister, so
no longer, you know, now we have a different type of an
organization. It's not we began here because this was a דרשה, drasha,
but after that it follows more of a logical organization. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like
this: ליתני להאי בבא לבסוף. lisni lehai bava libasof. But the גמרא
Gemara says okay, so you're going to include אחות אשתו achot ishto
when you get to the sister sort of section, but again, if
דרשות drashot are dominating and דרשות drashot come first, why don't you
have the whole sister section come at the bottom? Why don't you
have the sister section come after the wife section if the point
is to have דרשות drashot before non-דרשות? drashot?
So the גמרא Gemara says אלא ela fine, let's forget this whole
idea of דרשות. drashot. It's not about דרשות. drashot. There's a better
organization here and this is just, this is clearly the פשט. pshat.
תנא קורבי קורבי נקט. tana korvei korvei nakat. It's listing it in
order of degree of relation. תנא בתו ובת בתו ובת בנו דקורבי
עצמו. tana bito u'bat bito u'bat bno de'korvei atzmo. First you deal
with your own children: daughter, granddaughter, etc. Those are the people most
closely related to you.
ואיידי דתנא שלשה דורות למטה דידיה תנא נמי שלשה דורות למטה דידה.
ve'aidei de'tana shlosha dars lemata didei tana nami shlosha dars lemata didah.
So once you deal with, you know, your children and grandchildren, then
you deal with your wife's children and grandchildren. You know, if you
say which is the closest relation to you want to start with.
daughter you say more than sister, right? The only one perhaps more
than that is mother. It's interesting that mother isn't up here. I
could talk about that in a minute. But you got daughter, then
you might as well talk about daughter, let's talk about wife's daughters.
And as long as we're talking about going down generations, talk about
going up generations. So talk about wife's you know mother and grandmother.
When you say collateral, down lateral?
You know same direction.
Okay. The איידי דתנא aydi detana שלושה דורות למטה דידה shelosha dorot
lemata didah so and once you gave three generations down on her
side, so תנא שלושה דורות למעלה דידה tana shelosha dorot lemala didah
you do three generations up on her side, mother and grandmother. Then
once we did going down and going
up, ותנא אחותה vetana achota then we go
sideways, sister, ואחות אמה vaachot ima שקרובי עצמה shekrovei atzma then you
do a sister then people that are mother's sister you know wife's
sister you do all the sisters. So איידי דאיירי באיסור אחוה aydi
deayri beissur achva תני אחות אשתו tani achot ishto and once we're
dealing with you know relatives who are sisters like
אחות אמה achot ima like אחות אמה achot ima is more the
relative, אחותה achota and then אחות אמה achot ima and then אחות
אשתו achot ishto because
אחות אשתו achot ishto is not your like isn't a blood relative
but this is all the relatives so we did we did vertical
but we did that and then we did that and now we're
doing this way you know we're doing horizontal and once we're doing
horizontal blood relatives we also do אחות אשתו. achot ishto. Okay,
one minute. ותני אחותה ואחות אמה vetani achota vaachot ima okay, so
תני אחות אשתו tani achot ishto בדין הוא דלקדמה לכלתו מקמי אשת
אחיו שלא היה בעולמו badin hu dilekadmei lekallato mikamei eshet achiv shelo
haya beolamo דלאו משום קורבה הוא דאסירה delav mishum korva hu deassira
now it really should have had your son's wife before אשת אחיו
שלא היה בעולמו eshet achiv shelo haya beolamo once we got we
did sisters now into wives, okay, so כלתו kallato actually should have
been first. Why? Because כלתו kallato it says is because this is
not really אחות...
אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו eshet achiv shelo haya beolamo is really
not so much an איסור issur of קורבה korva doesn't start with
a concept of עריות arayot as much as it starts with a
concept of there was no מצות יבום. mitzat yibum. Right? Did Michael
explain to you what אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו eshet achiv shelo
haya beolamo, means? Is that somebody, somebody, שמעון Shimon died and ראובן
Reuven did חליצה chalitza to שמעון's's Shimon wife and then לוי Levi
was born. Okay, so so שמעון's's Shimon wife is now a a
woman that he never had a מצת יבום mitzat yibum toward. Right?
Is that clear? ראובן, Reuven, שמעון. Shimon. Okay,
so שמעון Shimon is married to this woman, okay, שמעון Shimon
dies, okay, ראובן Reuven goes ahead and does יבום yibum to her.
So this is step one, step two, and then step three then
לוי Levi is born. Okay, so now and you know ראובן Reuven
might might be married to another wife as well, wife number two.
Okay, so now ראובן Reuven dies, so לוי Levi he doesn't have
a מצת יבום mitzat yibum on wife number two because it's אסור
assur to do יבום yibum on wife number one. Why is it
אסור assur to do מצוה mitzvah on wife number one? Brother's wife,
big deal that's a מצות יבום mitzat yibum because it was also
a brother's wife that he didn't have a מצוה mitzvah of יבום
yibum with. It was שמעון's's Shimon wife and he didn't have a
מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum on שמעון's's Shimon wife because he wasn't
born yet. Okay, so that's considered אחות... you know, אשת אחיו שלא
היה בעולמו, eshet achiv shelo haya beolamo. he was never in the
world. So that is not really based on that fundamentally it's an
ערוה, erva, it's based on the idea that there was no מצות
יבום. mitzat yibum. Okay, so it really should have said כלתו kallato
before it said אשת אחיו eshet achiv. שלא היה בעולמו, דלא משום
קורבה הוא דאסירה dela mishum korva hu deassira that that it's not
because of קורבה korva that it's forbidden, אלא איידי דאיירי באיסור אחוה
ela aydi deayri beissur achva תני אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו tani
eshet achiv shelo haya beolamo but since we were dealing with sisters
so then when we're going to deal with wives we're going to
deal with wives of sisters. So אשת אחיו מאמו eshet achiv meimo
and אשת eshet? אחיו שלא היה בעולמו. achiv she'lo haya be'olamo. So
the sister idea, the you know sibling idea affected that the first
wives that we would mention would be wives of siblings and then
we would get to wife of son. Okay.
והדר תני כלתו vehadar tani kallato and then it said daughter-in-law. And
that actually is a good פשט pshat that exactly makes sense what
the organization is, right? You do vertical then you do horizontal then
it leads to this and that or whatever and that's fine, that's
the organization. Okay. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, now we're done with
the order. Now we get to another linguistic issue which is the
language of exempt. Why does it say they're exempt? Why doesn't it
say that they are forbidden to do יבום? yibum? Because then it
becomes once you're exempt you become forbidden then it becomes אשת אחיו.
So let's take a look.
ומאי איריא דתני פוטרות umai irya detani potrot why did it say
that they exempt their צרות? tzarot? ליתני אוסרות litnei osrot that the
צרות tzarot are forbidden to have יבום yibum done to them. No,
אי תנא אוסרות ei tana osrot if it had said forbid, הוי
אמינא אסור ליבום hava amina assur leyabem you don't
it's forbidden to do יבום yibum because that would be a type
of עריות arayot etc. אבל מיחלץ חלצה aval michlatz chaltza
maybe you should do חליצה, chalitza, you know because this is always
an issue, you have to be really serious when you say you're
פטור patur from יבום yibum and חליצה. chalitza. chalitzah. That means there's
no obligation. Right? If you wanted to come up with a rabbinic
stringency, you would say don't do יבום, yibbum, but there's still a
biblical obligation, you gotta get out of that, you gotta do חליצה.
chalitzah. And we do have some categories that are like that because
of ספק sofek or other rabbinic issues where we say don't do
יבום yibbum but do חליצה. chalitzah. So if you just had said
אסור, assur, you might have said אסור assur to do יבום yibbum
but maybe that's a rabbinic, maybe there's still a biblical issue going
on, maybe you still have to do חליצה. chalitzah. So therefore, not
to make that confusion, we said exempt, exempt means across the board.
Okay, אי תנא אוסר הוה אמינא אסור ליבם אבל מכלל חליצה, ei
tana oser hava amina assur leyabbem aval michlal chalitzah, you would have
to do חליצה, chalitzah, קא משמע לן. ka mashma lan. So the
גמרא Gemara says that's not an answer. וליתני אסורה לחלוץ, u-litni assura
lachlotz, be explicit, it's אסור assur to do חליצה, chalitzah, which means
that you don't do anything, חליצה chalitzah or יבום. yibbum. The גמרא
Gemara says, what do you mean it's אסור assur to do חליצה?
chalitzah? מאי קא עביד? mai ka avid? What do you mean? Why
should it be אסור assur to do חליצה? chalitzah? יבום yibbum is
אסור assur because it's an act of sex and it's עריות arayos
and חייב כרת chayav kares if it's not a מצוה mitzvah of
יבום. yibbum. But how could it be אסור assur to do חליצה?
chalitzah? What איסור issur is there about taking off a shoe and
spitting? The גמרא Gemara says no, no, don't, don't kid around. אלמה
לא? alma lo? How could it not be אסור? assur? אם אתה
אומר חולצת מתייבמת, im ata omer choletzes misyabbemes, we won't allow somebody
to do a חליצה. chalitzah. Oh, what big deal, just spitting and
taking off a shoe. No! Because you're sending a message that you
think that the מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibbum applies. That's the implicit
message you send when you do חליצה chalitzah and the next guy
who comes along is going to do יבום yibbum in this case.
So we won't let you do חליצה. chalitzah. So why did the
משנה Mishnah say exempt, just say אסור לחלוץ assur lachlotz and I
could have figured everything else out. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
no. כיון דבמקום מצוה הוא דאסירה צרה ושלא במקום מצוה שריא משום
הכי תנא פוטרות. kevan debimakom mitzvah hu de-assira tzara ve-shelo bimakom mitzvah
sharya mishum hachi tana potrot.
So we're going to find out in a later משנה Mishnah that,
let's say that this idea of צרה, tzara, how does the idea
of צרה tzara of ערווה erva affecting צרה tzara work? Okay, just
conceptually what it's saying is, is I don't have a מצוה mitzvah
to do יבום yibbum to this woman who's an, who's my daughter,
sister, whatever. And therefore, it doesn't create an איסור ערווה issur erva
on the other woman, it says there's no מצוה יבום mitzvah yibbum
on the other woman and since there's no מצוה יבום mitzvah yibbum
then automatically she becomes forbidden as my brother's wife. So conceptually the
way it works is it removes the מצוה יבום. mitzvah yibbum. How
would it be different if I would have communicated the idea as:
she makes her co-wife forbidden. I did not frame it in terms
of יבום, yibbum, I just said she makes her co-wife forbidden. Well,
then I would have said, let's take another scenario. Let's say my
daughter is married to a man who I'm not related to. Okay,
married to,
I don't know, עשו, Esau, but actually as רש״י Rashi says נכרי,
nochri, but רש״י Rashi doesn't mean נכרי nochri a non-Jew, he means
a non-relative. Okay, so let's say anyway, so let's say my daughter
is married to somebody I'm not related to and he's also married
to another woman. And this guy dies. No יבום, yibbum, whatever, just
a stranger she's married to. Okay, so if I would have said,
"Oh, my daughter makes a co-wife forbidden to me," then I would
have said I can't marry this stranger's co-wife because he was also
married to my daughter and my daughter makes the co-wife forbidden. So
you can't say the עריות arayos makes the other woman forbidden, that's
not the mechanism. The mechanism is she removes the מצוה יבום. mitzvah
yibbum. And since she removes the מצוה יבום, mitzvah yibbum, then automatically
the other woman is forbidden as my brother's wife. But if they
were married to a stranger, then I would be able to marry
the other woman, right? So that's what it's saying, and that's really
a really good answer. It had to say פוטרות potrot because that's
exactly the mechanism. The mechanism of how things are working is that
the מצוה יבום mitzvah yibbum no longer applies. It's not a mechanism
that an ערווה erva makes a co-wife forbidden to the man. Okay,
so that's what it says. It says כיון דבמקום מצוה הוא דאסירה
צרה, kevan debimakom mitzvah hu de-assira tzara, the צרה, tzara,
the co-wife becomes forbidden in a context of מצוה mitzvah meaning in
a case of brother's wife. ושלא במקום מצוה שריא, ve-shelo bimakom mitzvah
sharya, if it's not a context of מצוה, mitzvah, it's not a
brother's
wife, then a צרה tzara to an ערווה erva is still permitted
to a man if they're not married to his brother. משום הכי
תנא פוטרות, mishum hachi tana potrot, therefore it says you exempt from
מצוה יבום, mitzvah yibbum, that's the mechanism, not a mechanism of making
the other woman forbidden. So the גמרא Gemara says: ומאי אריא דתני
מן החליצה ומן היבום? u-mai arya detani min hachalitzah u-min hayibbum? Fine.
So now we've solved that. We've solved the order, right? We're going
through the whole thing. חמש עשרה נשים פוטרות הן וצרותיהן chamesh esreh
nashim potrot hen ve-tzaroteihen etc.
So we got the order, we got the word פוטרות. potrot. The
last linguistic issue we're going to ask is why did it say
מן החלוצה—what did it say? מן החליצה min hachalitzah... ומן היבום
and not מן היבום ומן החליצה, min hayibbum u-min hachalitzah, right? If
you were learning this מסכת Masechet with a חברותא chavruta and he
started asking these questions, you would probably say could you please just
focus on the real issues and not ask these types of questions?
But the גמרא Gemara is, like I said, this opening סוגיא Sugya
focuses on these types of linguistic issues. So let's take a look.
So it says like this, ומאי אריא דתני מן החליצה ומן היבום,
u-mai arya detani min hachalitzah u-min hayibbum, why does it say מן
החליצה... אי תני מן היבום *Ei tani min hayibum* if it just
say you're exempt from יבום *yibum* since יבום *yibum* is the מצוה
*mitzvah*, the prime מצוה *mitzvah* is יבום *yibum* and everything else follows
that. No, so it says like this: no. אי תני מן היבום
*Ei tani min hayibum* if it just say you're exempt from יבום
*yibum* הוה אמינא *hava amina* מיחלץ חלצה יבומי לא מיבמה *michlatz chaltza
yibumi lo mivama* going back to the point: I might have thought
fine, you don't do יבום *yibum* but you'll do חליצה *chalitza*, play
it safe, maybe there's still a biblical issue that needs to be
addressed, maybe it's only a rabbinic reason you don't do יבום *yibum*.
So, you know, there's always the possibility that there are some women
that you don't do יבום *yibum* for, but you do חליצה *chalitza*
for because of ספק *safek* or other issues. So therefore you could
not just say פטורה מן היבום *ptura min hayibum*. Okay. הוה אמינא
מיחלץ חלצה יבומי לא מיבמה *hava amina michlatz chaltza yibumi lo mivama*,
do חליצה *chalitza* don't do יבום *yibum*. קא משמע לן *ka mashma
lan* that no. כל העולה ליבום עולה לחליצה *kol ha'oleh leyibum oleh
lachalitza*, anybody obligated in יבום *yibum* is a, you know, חליצה *chalitza*
applies to. וכל שאינו עולה ליבום אינו עולה לחליצה *vechol she'eino oleh
leyibum eino oleh lachalitza*, if there's no obligation of יבום *yibum* there's
no חליצה *chalitza*. Now, it does not mean that there won't be
women that you do חליצה *chalitza* and not יבום *yibum*. That could
be because of ספק *safek*, so if there's a ספק *safek* whether
you're able to do יבום *yibum*, you're not allowed to do it
but you have to do חליצה *chalitza*, or if there's a rabbinic
reason why you don't do יבום *yibum*. But at a biblical level,
if you don't do one, you don't do the other. They go
together. And therefore, in what? Package deal. And therefore we didn't want
you to misunderstand that, so we made it clear that exempt from
both. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says fine, you gotta say both,
but why did you, why was your order חליצה *chalitza* first? The
order should have been יבום *yibum* first. יבום *yibum* is the more
important one. וליתני מן היבום ומן החליצה *velitni min hayibum umin hachalitza*?
אי נמי מן החליצה לחודא *ei nami min hachalitza lachuda*? Just say
exempt from חליצה *chalitza*. Why say חליצה *chalitza* and יבום *yibum*, do
both of them and do it in that order? So the גמרא
Gemara. *Gemara* says אבא שאול היא *Abba Shaul hi*, it's going like
אבא שאול *Abba Shaul*, דאמר מצות חליצה קודמת למצות יבום *de'amar mitzvat
chalitza kodemet lemitzvat yibum*, that actually, that we encourage people to do
חליצה *chalitza* before יבום *yibum*. I mean, people might know if you've
ever heard about these cases, right, in Ashkenazi communities that's completely correct,
that, you know, people basically even if the surviving brother is not
married, you know, basically told you're supposed to do חליצה *chalitza*. In
Sephardic communities, at least in some of them, they actually say no,
what do you mean, the basic מצוה *mitzvah* is a מצוה *mitzvah*
of יבום *yibum*, and therefore especially it's also more possible to have
that approach if you don't have a, you know, a culture and
a principle of מנהג *minhag*, so polygamy is a possibility, you can
also have a general approach about saying that we prioritize יבום *yibum*.
Now, why to not prioritize יבום *yibum* is quite fascinating. And if
you take a look at רש"י Rashi *Rashi* at the bottom, he
quotes, I mean, we'll see more of this in the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*, but two lines from the bottom רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says, אבא
שאול היא בפרק החולץ אבא שאול אומר הכונס יבמתו לשום נוי לשום
אישות כאילו פוגע בערוה *Abba Shaul hi beperek hacholetz Abba Shaul omer
hachones yevamto leshum noy leshum ishut ke'ilu pogeah be'erva*, because you might
actually want to do יבום *yibum* because you actually are attracted to
this woman, or maybe you actually really do want to marry this
woman, you'd want to marry her if she wasn't your brother's wife.
Now we would think what's wrong with that if you're already doing
יבום *yibum*, hopefully there could be, to develop some relationship here. No,
then it's no longer לשם מצוה *leshem mitzvah*, then it's, then it's
more of, you know, a normal type of a, it's a normal
type of an attraction and a, you know, and a marriage that's
not about the מצוה *mitzvah*. וקרוב בעיני להיות הולד ממזר *vekarov be'einai
lihyot havlad mamzer*, it's, it's practically like an
איסור issur, אשת אח *issur eshet ach* if you're not doing it
in the framework and the mentality of doing it all לשם שמים
*leshem shamayim*. Okay, so that's pretty heavy, right? Because we would say
like if you gotta do it, you might as well, you know,
the better place to do it is when actually maybe they're interested
in getting married to one another. So that's his approach. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says following that approach, we mentioned חליצה *chalitza* first
to underscore that חליצה *chalitza* is the preferred mode. Okay. Now, fine.
Now we're done with the order, we're done with, with the phrase
of פוטרות *potrot*, and we're done with why it says חליצה *chalitza*
before יבום *yibum*.
וליתני סדר חליצה *velitni seder chalitza*.
Well yeah, but then it wouldn't have emphasized it comes first and
it would have just been felt to picked one arbitrarily. If you
say both and you put it first, it makes more of the
point. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says מנינא דרישא למעוטי
מאי מנינא דסיפא למעוטי מאי *minyana derisha lema'utei mai minyana deseifa lema'utei
mai*? We're still not done. Why did it have to say fifteen?
I know how to count. And why did it have to say
at the end "these women are פטור *patur*"? It seems like it's
trying to give you an exact list. What is it trying to
exclude by this list? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says למעוטי דרב
ודרב אסי l'mautei d'Rav u'd'Rav Assi. *lema'utei derav vederav Assi*, to exclude
רב Rav *Rav* and רב אסי Rav Assi *Rav Assi*. רב Rav
*Rav* and רב אסי Rav Assi? *Rav Assi* wanted to add to
this list. How did they want to add to this list other
women who are exempt? So רב Rav *Rav* had a case about
a צרת סוטה tzarat sotah. *tzarat sotah*. A man's wife basically has
committed adultery or suspected of committing adultery, but let's even make it
easy, committed adultery. So he's no longer allowed to have sex with
his wife. Okay. Now, then let's say, let's forget צרה tzarah *tzarah*
a minute. Then the man dies. Does the brother have to do
יבום *yibum*? Well, this is a principle of: the brother is only
doing יבום *yibum* because the dead brother, if he were alive, would
have, would have the possibility of having sex with his wife and
having a child. This man who himself could not have had sex
with his wife, so the brother isn't obligated to take the place.
That was not a union that was actually a viable union. in
terms of conceiving a child, having sex and conceiving a child. So
in that case, he's exempt from ייבום. yibbum Let's say this woman
who had committed adultery, she has a co-wife. Well, if you're exempt
from doing ייבום yibbum to one woman, you're exempt from doing ייבום
yibbum to the other woman. So that's the case about צרת סוטה.
Sotah That's רב's Rav case. What's רב אסי's Rav Assi case? Excuse
me.
So רב Rav says the צרה tzarah is exempt from ייבום yibbum
by our משנה Mishnah right thank you by our משנה Mishnah listing
only 15, it's not denying that you don't do ייבום yibbum to
the woman who committed adultery, but you would do ייבום yibbum to
the צרה tzarah because she's not really an ערוה, ervah, right? The
idea here, all of these are עריות, arayot, right? The case about
a man and סוטה Sotah, and his wife who's a סוטה, Sotah
okay whatever, she's not an ערוה ervah to you, it's just the
problem here is about their relationship, right? That's where that's why there's
no ייבום yibbum because that relationship is a broken relationship. Okay, so
it's not an ערוה ervah idea. So רב Rav says nevertheless צרה
tzarah is also exempt. Whereas so what the גמרא Gemara is saying
is, no, the משנה Mishnah says only 15 to say in this
case you don't do ייבום yibbum with the woman who's who committed
adultery, but you still do ייבום yibbum with the צרה tzarah. because
it doesn't exempt the צרה.
tzarah Wait, wait, wait, why is that different than the נמצאת איילונית?
nimtzet aylonit?
Right, because נמצאת איילונית nimtzet aylonit is yeah but נמצאת איילונית nimtzet
aylonit isn't an איסור, issur, it's just not able to, right? And
then there's the whole question is it even a מקח טעות mekach
taut question, but that's just not physically able to. Here there's a
real איסור, issur. so it becomes exactly. But yes, that's a good
point. We will see all of this when we get to one
minute. What's רב אסי? Rav Assi So רב אסי's Rav Assi case
is צרת איילונית. tzarat aylonit. Oh there you go Joe. So רב
אסי Rav Assi actually says the case of now איילונית aylonit is
different. So רב Rav, says a סוטה Sotah and רב אסי Rav
Assi says איילונית. aylonit. Now איילונית aylonit is a woman that can't
have children, okay, and again the problem here is not that she's
an ערוה, ervah, but that but that there's a problem with the
relationship the initial marriage, the initial relationship and its ability to conceive
children. So there you go. So she might actually say then, he
might not. We'll see that in the גמרא. Gemara Obviously there's a
difference here because here it's not physically possible it's not just an
איסור. issur So both of them say that even when it's not
an ערוה, ervah, if there's no ייבום yibbum with one of the
women even if it's because of their relationship to the first husband,
that creates an איסור issur of צרה tzarah as well, whereas the
גמרא Gemara saying that our משנה Mishnah would be rejecting that and
saying that actually no ייבום yibbum would still apply to the צרה
tzarah because this is not about ערוה. ervah. Let's just read the
answer then takes the question. So the גמרא Gemara says למעוטי דרב
ודרב אסי. So the גמרא Gemara says ולרב ולרב אסי למעוטי מאי?
u'l'Rav u'l'Rav Assi l'mautei mai?
So that's very nice. But רב Rav and רב אסי Rav Assi
would like to believe that their cases are not rejected by the
משנה. Mishnah. So if they would like to believe that they're correct
and that the principle of צרה tzarah. does apply in their cases,
why is our משנה Mishnah saying only 15? So the גמרא Gemara
says like this. אי סבירא להו דהדדי, ei sevira lehu d'hadadei, so
if רב Rav, holds of רב אסי Rav Assi and רב אסי
Rav Assi holds of רב, Rav they basically agree with one another,
then חדא למעוטי צרת ממאנת וחדא למעוטי צרת מחזיר גרושתו. chada l'mautei
tzarat m'ma'enet v'chada l'mautei tzarat machzir gerushato.
So there's two other cases that they would agree you don't have
a principle of צרה. tzarah What would that be? One would be
ממאנת m'ma'enet and the other is מחזיר גרושתו. machzir gerushato. Let me
just sort of read to the end and then I'll explain it.
ואי לא סבירא להו דהדדי, v'ei lo sevira lehu d'hadadei, and maybe
if they don't hold of one another, רב Rav doesn't hold of
רב אסי Rav Assi and רב אסי Rav Assi doesn't hold of
רב, so חדא למעוטי דחבריה, chada l'mautei d'chavreih, so one of the
because it says 15 in the beginning and it repeats these are
the one so it sounds like there are two things being rejected.
So one thing being rejected is the one the other one holds
of, right? Either the case of סוטה sotah or איילונית. aylonit. וחדא
למעוטי v'chada l'mautei and the other is to exclude אידך ממאנת או
צרת מחזיר גרושתו. idach m'ma'enet o tzarat machzir gerushato. Again
one of the other two, ממאנת m'ma'enet or מחזיר גרושתו. machzir gerushato.
So what the גמרא says is in addition to these two cases
which they say does have a צרה tzarah and we could say
the משנה Mishnah is rejecting but they wouldn't want to say the
משנה's Mishnah rejecting their case, they would want to say yes the
idea of צרה tzarah applies here, so we have two other cases
that they agree that the principle of צרה tzara does not apply.
What are they? ממאנת m'ma'enet and מחזיר גרושתו. machzir gerushato.
So what are these cases? So ממאנת m'ma'enet wait let me just
double check רש"י Rashi about one thing.
Okay. So basically here's what you have.
You have that you have this man here's ראובן Reuven and he's
married to two women. He's married to to רחל Rachel and לאה.
Leah. It just so happens that רחל Rachel as we know was
well no let's just go anyway. Okay. So he's married to רבקה
Rivka and לאה. Leah. So רבקה Rivka was very young she was
three years old, okay.
She's she's three years old. Actually she's really just less than 12.
Okay.
So that it's only a rabbinic marriage, okay. It's מאמר ma'amar Michael
spoke about that if it wasn't if the father didn't marry her
off, okay. She was married off by the brothers or the
mother. Anyway these you
know there's no עריות arayos here. There's no עריות arayos no nothing.
It's just one of his wives is under is underage. He
dies. Now שמעון Shimon can he go ahead and do ייבום yibbum.
to to רבקה? Rivka? Well that's a tricky thing because רבקה Rivka
wasn't הלכתית halachically really ראובן's Reuven wife. So we'll get to all
of that. But because the idea is that the relationship that ראובן
Reuven has sort of pseudo transfers to שמעון Shimon that's called like
זיקה. zika. Right שמעון Shimon now has a quasi like an un
attachment an un sort of like a you know a potential relationship
an attachment that can be fully made manifest through the act of
ייבום. yibbum. It's like you know it's sort of seen as this
as this you know partial thing that can become fully actualized through
the act of ייבום. yibbum It sort of transfers from ראובן Reuven
to שמעון Shimon the relationship. So the same way רבקה Rivka could
do מיאון mi'un to ראובן Reuven רבקה Rivka could go ahead and
do מיאון mi'un to שמעון Shimon and she's getting out of it.
She did מיאון mi'un and she's walking away and you can no
longer do and you can no longer do ייבום yibbum to her.
And we'll find out why it has to do with rabbinic whole
sort of range of rabbinic it has to do with rabbinic considerations.
But that's the case of ממאנת. mema'enes. So the whole that whole
thing is all like דרבנן. derabbanan. You know the whole thing through
relationship to ראובן Reuven her מיאון mi'un to שמעון Shimon everything is
דרבנן. derabbanan. So even though in this case once she's done מיאון
mi'un and it breaks the relationship שמעון Shimon can no longer do
ייבום yibbum to רבקה Rivka he can still do ייבום yibbum with
לאה. Leah. So that would be the case of צרת ממאנת. tzaras
mema'enes. Hard enough to understand why he can't do it with רבקה
Rivka not a חידוש chiddush that he can still do it with
לאה. Leah. That's this case. מחזיר גרושתו Machzir grushaso is a lot
easier. ראובן Reuven went ahead and he was married to לאה Leah
then he divorced
her then he remarried her. So he was מחזיר גרושתו. machzir grushaso.
And then he's also got another wife רחל Rachel that he never
divorced.
We should make this יעקב.
Yaakov. So we'll rewrite the biblical story. He divorced לאה Leah and
he remarried her and he wasn't allowed to if she was then
with another man. But he always was married to רחל. Rachel. And
then יעקב Yaakov dies. So in this case because he's not allowed
to be married to לאה Leah there's no ייבום yibbum. on לאה.
Leah. But there would still be a case of רחל Rachel there
still would be ייבום. yibbum It would be different than the case
of סוטה sotah. because the איסור issur of מחזיר גרושתו machzir grushaso
is of a different quality than the איסור issur of סוטה. sotah
Let me just see if רש״י Rashi spells it out meaning meaning
that meaning that there would not be a concept of צרה tzara.
there. It would not be a problem. Right.
So I mean we'll see why later the גמרא doesn't explain it
but it's similar to the idea of סוטה sotah where there's a
prohibition of them having sex but here the איסור issur of מחזיר
גרושתו machzir grushaso is more about him remarrying her than about the
איסור of sex and therefore whatever it's of a different quality. And
we will see therefore so in these cases you would be able
to do ייבום yibbum with the צרה. tzara So when the משנה
Mishna is saying there are fifteen that it affects the צרה tzara.
as well it's minimally excluding these two. These two could be cases
where you don't do ייבום yibbum with the wife but you'd still
do ייבום yibbum with the צרה. tzara Yes.
Just a very quick question in our משנה Mishna it just says
חמש עשרה chamesh esreh and it lists the fifteen that but it
would be the same idea
for סוטה sotah ייבום yibbum wouldn't apply because no קידושין kiddushin comes
from this.
Right probably yeah I'm pretty sure that's correct. I'm pretty sure that's
correct. Okay so let's just get a little bit further. גמרא says
like this. So the גמרא says like this.
So
finally according to
רב and רב אסי ליתנינהו? lisninhu? So according to רב and רב
אסי that there is a צרה tzara idea here by סוטה sotah
or by אילונית ailonis the צרה tzara is also exempt. They have
to explain why it's not in the משנה. Mishna. If it's really
true that these women just as much as עריות arayos exempt their
צרה tzara then why are these two not listed in the
משנה? Mishna? Good question right? So the גמרא says is no לפי
שאינו בצרת צרה.
lefi she'eino
betzaras tzara. Because even if the סוטה's co-wife would be exempt if
she went and she remarried and she married another brother she would
not exempt the next derivation the צרה tzara. of the צרה. tzara
I'm not going to sort of explain why right now. In the
משנה Mishna they all exempt the צרה tzara and the צרת צרה.
tzaras tzara. So you see we've totally confused you here but what
we've managed to do like some of these opening סוגיות sugyos do
is give you a window into some of the stuff that's coming
up some of the real complicated stuff like oh my god there's
all these other possibilities of women you don't do ייבום to that
maybe you still do it with the צרה tzara or maybe you
do it with the צרה but not
with the צרת צרה tzaras tzara and so on.
So we've introduced all these other categories which we will get to
later.
Let's I guess we will have to end here so it's. We
already have gotten us behind. We’ll have to pick up the pace.
But I’ll say one thing before we end. I just want to
point to רש"י Rashi on the משנה, Mishnah, which I just thought
was fascinating, which we won’t get another chance to point to. But
if you take a look at רש"י Rashi on the משנה, Mishnah,
he says fourth wide line, or the end of the third wide
line from the top, from the very top, third line from the
top,
דצרת צרתה עד סוף העולם, desoras soroson ad sof ha'olam, רש"י Rashi
says
במתניתין מפרש. b'masnisin meforesh. Like רש"י Rashi often says בגמרא מפרש. b'gemara
meforesh. Right? What does this משנה Mishnah mean? Oh, the גמרא will
explain what the משנה Mishnah means. Here רש"י is saying the משנה
Mishnah later on will tell you what it means. And if you
notice, the משנה Mishnah was quite fascinating in its sort of almost
self-reflective way, right, when the way the משנה Mishnah said, oh, what
do we mean by this? Here’s what we mean. And it spelled
out the scenario. Right? You saw that in the משנה Mishnah yesterday.
So I thought it was very interesting, רש"י says במתניתין מפרש. b'masnisin
meforesh. You know, if you don’t understand this line of the משנה,
Mishnah, wait until later down in the משנה, Mishnah, it’ll become clear.
Okay, so.